Breakfast Club morning everybody is dej
envy Angela ye Charlemagne the guy we
are the breakfast club we have a special
guest in the building yes 2020
presidential candidate yes right
Andrew yang welcome sir oh it's great to
be here thank you so much for having me
how's everything with Jill morning
morning yeah this is a real privilege so
thank you
who is Andrew yang for people who don't
know all what do want me to start I'm an
entrepreneur who's spent the last six
and a half years running an organization
I started called venture for America
that helped create several thousand jobs
in Detroit Cleveland Baltimore st. Louis
Birmingham and other cities around the
country and I realized that the reason
why Donald Trump won the election there
are a lot of reasons they're a bunch of
them but one of the big ones is that we
automated away four million
manufacturing jobs in Michigan Ohio
Pennsylvania Wisconsin Missouri Iowa all
the swing states he needed to win and my
friends in Silicon Valley and I've got a
lot of them know that what we did to the
manufacturing workers we're now gonna do
to the retail workers that call center
workers the fast-food workers the truck
drivers and on and on through the
economy
so I went to Washington was like hey
what are we gonna do about the fact that
when the third inning of the greatest
economic and technological
transformation in the history of the
country and the answers I got were
really disappointing too horrifying and
I worked in the Obama administration I
was a presidential or as I called the
the good White House and so a lot of
people I was talking to were Democrats
and for whatever reason no one wanted to
actually rise to this particular
challenge and so I'm running for
president to help us evolve in advance
to the next stage of our economy was a
lot of things that you said just now
number one it was the black house when
you was there okay cuz Obama was running
it but you wrote a book on the war on
normal people right here human jobs
that's a lot of people's fear so you see
that it's very scary but a lot of people
don't address it they act like
technology and automation is a great
thing and we're gonna hire people who
are gonna control the automation but in
reality a lot of people will be out of
jobs music coming like oh it's not just
coming it's already been happening and
if you look at the numbers
we lost four million manufacturing jobs
to automation over the last number of
years and if you go to Detroit or
Cleveland or st. Louis you see the
aftermath and I studied economics in
college and so according to economic
theory all those workers would get
retrained rescaled find new jobs and all
would be well but then when you actually
go to the communities you see that about
half of them left the workforce and
never worked again and of that group
about half filed for disability then you
saw a massive surge in alcohol use and
drug overdose oppression suicides and
depression and so there's a lot of
despair a lot of suffering and it's
going unaddressed around the country and
unfortunately it's just gonna ramp up so
one of the things I'm trying to tell
people is like look this is no longer
speculative this is not like oh we
should keep our eye on this this has
been ripping a hole in our communities
in our society for years now and it's
about to pick up steam so why a trump
support is worried about Mexicans who
need to be worried about the robots
taking the jobs that's my exact point
man it is not immigrants immigrants have
nothing to do with the economic distress
many Americans are feeling it's the fact
that technology is advancing to a point
where our labor is less and less central
to the economy so yeah what do we do
about that solution so the solution I'm
proposing and anyone who's heard about
my campaign knows this I'm proposing
that we declare a dividend of $1,000 a
month for every American adult starting
at age 18 that's the universal basic
income yes the universal basic income
which I rebranded the freedom dividend
because it tests better with more
Americans with the word freedom in it
and so a lot of a lot of us have never
achieved true liberation in this country
yeah I mean it's a truth it's one reason
why Martin Luther King championed this
plan in principle in 1967 the year
before he was assassinated I called it
the guaranteed minimum income Thomas
Paine was 40 at the founding of the
country there's a very American idea so
it seems far out to us now that hey we
should just have a dividend where
everyone gets a thousand bucks a month
but we've been talking about this for
decades and it came this close to being
law in 1971 it actually passed the House
of Representatives twice under Richard
Nixon Milton Friedman and a thousand
economists signed a study saying
this would be great for America and then
one state has had a dividend for 37
years where everyone in that state gets
between 1 and 2 thousand dollars a year
no questions asked they did it that's
Alaska yeah you go to Alaska right now
you live there for a year and everyone
in your family gets between 1 and 2
thousand dollars a year from the
petroleum dividend it was past 37 years
ago by a Republican governor and Alaska
is a deep red state this Republican
governor shows up 1982 and he's like hey
there's a lot of oil money who would you
rather get it the government who's just
gonna screw it up or you the Alaskan
people and then the Alaskans said us
please and he's like I thought you'd say
that and suddenly they passed his
dividend and now it's wildly popular has
created thousands of jobs has improved
children's health as a decreased income
inequality and what I'm going around the
country saying is look what Alaska is
doing with oil money we can do for the
entire country
with technology money so what exactly is
the universal basic income the universal
basic income is a policy where every
everyone in a society gets a certain
amount of money free and clear to do
whatever they want no questions asked
can I ask you this if you make a decent
amount of money then you don't get that
universal basic income or do you get
that in addition to what you make oh you
get it in addition to what you make this
is a right of citizenship has nothing to
do with your income employment status
everyone gets it so you say technology
would yeah so right now and you guys see
that headlines Amazon paid zero in taxes
last year despite record profits Netflix
paid zero in taxes last year despite
record profits and it's not their fault
as just our systems really poorly
designed to have the American public
benefit from new innovations and
advances in technology and that's the
trap worried because I was just in Iowa
I'm sound very politician when I say
that shit but I was just in Iowa at a
truck stop and there were truck truckers
wall-to-wall and those jobs are exactly
the jobs that are going to be displaced
in the next five to ten years and so who
wins who wins from artificial
intelligence who wins from all the new
innovations it's going to be Amazon
Google uber Facebook the biggest tech
companies that will have the AI that
will then start displacing workers and
the American people will not see much
money from that at all adrià is selling
this all wrong
build a wall around Silicon
that's a question a load the wall it's
that but what made you want to run for
president is it the fact that Donald
Trump was an entrepreneur and made it in
or was it something that you were
looking at for a long time because we're
starting to see more and more
entrepreneurs people that don't
necessarily know or started in politics
really jump into the presidential
campaign I certainly would never be
running for president if a number of
things had not happened
the main one that Donald Trump won in
2016 so imagine being the guy who's
getting medals from the White House for
creating jobs around the country
realizing that your work is like pouring
water into a bathtub as a giant hole
ripped in the bottom Wow and that the
Middle's you're getting are nonsense
really like you're getting Pat's in the
back we're doing stuff that's not
actually gonna solve the problem and the
problem leads to Donald Trump and for
whatever reason no one wants to talk
about it and that's why I'm running for
president I'm a parent I've got two
young boys who are six and three and I'm
not gonna bring them up in a country
that's going to fall apart around them
which is right now where we are going to
go if we keep scapegoating immigrants
and people have nothing to do with the
problems we're experiencing instead of
focusing on the facts on the ground
which is that technology is driving our
economy to to you know to places that
it's never been why should I vote some
but for somebody with zero legislative
experience I feel like that's what the
mistake that we made this time not weak
that evil form but you know I was hoping
what I've been going around saying is
like look Donald Trump is a bad present
because he's a bad president you know
it's not like all entrepreneurs are
Donald Trump and as an entrepreneur most
entrepreneurs feel like Donald Trump
gives us all a bad name and he's more of
a marketing charlatan then he is a real
builder or someone who elevates people
and build strong teams and organizations
so it's up to the American people to
decide what kind of background they want
but I would suggest that the American
people have been casting about for some
kind of change agent for years because
we've sensed that our government is
falling way behind the curve he was
different so Donald Trump wins on that
but then you see Bernie Sanders achieve
outside success last time because again
people see that we need to make big
changes and even Barack Obama's election
in 2008 I voted for him twice
you can see the American people have
been hungry for some sort of accelerant
to help catch up and modernize our
government because we know Washington DC
is stuck decades in the past you know of
course you know being an entrepreneur
and I noticed that a lot of
entrepreneurs and a lot of people that
make a lot of money usually vote
Republican just because of the tax
breaks and things like that so why are
you voting towards Democrat or why are
you running as a Democrat opposed to
Republican which I would feel that most
entrepreneurs of people with some long
Bank are well if you look at my
background you know I mean I went to
Brown University so you know what they
went to brown and his brother went to
Wesleyan and I went to Wesleyan yeah
yeah but if you look at my my platform
it lines up with Democrat and
progressive priorities really across the
board on everything from reproductive
rights to to gay rights to gun safety to
everything else so it was very natural I
mean I was again part of the Obama
administration running as a Democrat was
very natural what what is your a
universal basic income plain how much do
you want to give a thousand a month
every every American adult gets a
thousand dollars a month starting at age
18 and that would be a game-changer for
tens of millions of American families
because we know 78 percent of Americans
are living paycheck to paycheck 57
percent can't afford an unexpected $500
bill and what I'm telling people's look
we have the money
like our economy's up to 20 trillion
dollars up five trillion in the last 12
years alone we're the richest most
advanced economy in the history of the
world we can easily afford $1,000 a
month yeah until I die
okay 64 well yeah it's until you die but
if you have Social Security than it
overlaps you don't get both inflation
no well not why not well I'll give you a
couple data points on the inflation so
we printed four trillion dollars for the
banks during the bailout and there was
no inflation in consumer goods and if
you look at what's happening right now
in your own life a lot of stuffs getting
cheaper or better that's electronics
clothing cars media food for the most
part all that stuff staying essentially
cost in a price or getting cheaper or
more sophisticated now what's going up
in price what's driving us all crazy
housing education health care and those
three three things are not being driven
by the fact that we've lots of money to
spend it's not being driven by like
purchasing power Healthcare is being
driven by the private insurance industry
and the fact you have this opaque
pricing and you're not actually you know
negotiating price for any interaction
education is because college has gone up
in price two hundred fifty percent and
families feel they have no choice but to
pay so they just take out massive loans
which is its own huge set of problems
that we have to try and address and I
would forgive a lot of student loans
because I think a lot of them were
immorally generated and it's a stimulus
to the economy young people should be
starting families buying homes starting
businesses and not paying off this
phantom student loan debt
sadly me yeah I I had 100 K in law
school debt for years I used to call it
my mistress I was like writing a check
every month to some like family in
another town like I hope they're in a
good time on so I get it like you know
people should not be just servicing this
loan forever it doesn't make any sense
and then housing housing is the
trickiest one housing is because we feel
like we have to live in certain areas in
order to access certain economic
opportunities so like the housing prices
in New York and San Francisco obviously
gone through the roof and part of that
is local part of that is zoning
ordinances and you can't develop
affordable housing but the point of it
is is that we're not increasing the
money supply by enough that you would
see massive inflation and the way most
consumer products work is that they'll
still be price sensitivity among
consumers and competition among firms
for your business there's no reason
you'd see a massive spike in prices you
don't think corporations would say ok I
know everybody's getting $1,000 and
whatnot so let's raise the prices a
little bit well then so on just regular
everyday products oh yeah so what I say
to people is like look let's say you're
you're in Missouri and then president
yang 2021 I'm like freedom vivid in time
let's do this thing and then the checks
are going out and then you're like the
burger joint and you're like ooh
everyone's got a thousand bucks a month
I'm gonna raise my burger prices from 5
bucks to 10 bucks if you walk in that
burger joint you're gonna be like what
the heck happened this is five bucks
last week and then you're gonna go to
the taco place of the deli and then
every restaurant has to try and go juice
Dainius Lee and then it just takes one
restaurant to be like you know what I'm
not doing that
I'm not doing that and then everyone
goes to that restaurant and then they're
all like oh I can't turns out I can't
stick it to people because it's not like
if you get a thousand bucks a month
you're all of a sudden made of money
yeah to get some basic things now what
about healthcare before you do that but
youyou said we have money when you said
we have a lot of money but a debt of
like sixteen trillion dollars that we
owe yeah so it's a little more than that
actually but so one thing I'm saying to
people's like look we have the money I
mean again Amazon paid zero taxes like
Jeff Bezos is worth 160 billion dollars
for a reason you know what I mean like
there's a lot of wealth in our society
right that's and it's gonna be good okay
so the fact that we've got a lot of past
mismanagement and a lot of waste in the
system does not mean we do not have the
money we have the money all right now
what about our universal health care do
you believe that along with this
universal basic income we should also
have universal health care oh yeah
hundred percent I'm for a single-payer
medicare-for-all it makes no sense to
have Americans more stressed out about
paying for care than we are getting well
if we get sick or injured or our kids
get sick or injured it's backwards it's
immoral and I'll tell you there's
another thing where people like where
you get the money where you gonna get
the money we spend eighteen percent of
GDP on our health care twice as much as
other countries two worst results we
have plenty of money it's just the
money's not on the public bottom line
yet but it should be so I've been the
CEO of a business I'll tell people very
honestly like our health care system
makes it harder to hire people it makes
it harder to treat people like full-time
employees because you just want to turn
them all into contractors and say hey it
makes it harder to start a business
makes it harder to change jobs it's
actually this giant impediment on our
economic dynamism and growth how many
people out there have businesses that
they might have started if our health
care was covered by the public sector
which it should be so so I'm for
universal in the future most people are
gonna be freelancers just because
companies are trying to just hire a
contractor so they don't have to pay for
health care
yeah ninety-four percent of the new jobs
created in this country since 2000
five have been temporary gig or contract
jobs so tying that don't have healthcare
benefits so tying health care to your
job makes less and less sense and we
just need to get with the program and
evolve and say look your job in
healthcare are unrelated yeah like you
said a lot of people don't want to take
that jump because they know if they
leave their nine-to-five they lose
health care and their family loses
health care I don't want to take that
job to be able to I'm gonna tell you
guys a true story like I told my wife I
was have opposed to I know I'm supposed
to everything else is I know this is
true story go to my wife and I say hey
Bea I'm gonna run for president and her
first question is what I'm gonna do
about health care DBI once said they
wanted to get rid of welfare and social
service program so wouldn't that leave
people who qualify for all these
benefits in like worse economic
positions because they'll have to pay
for their own health care and child care
and that is totally not my plan I mean
there there are people that have been
for ubi in the past who are like oh
we're gonna like get rid of all the
social services I think that's crazy you
can't take away programs that people are
literally relying upon for their day to
day a month a month survival it'd be
vastly destructive so my plan is to make
the freedom dividend available to
everyone and it's like a parallel
supplement to the existing program on
top of everything they're already
getting so what I'm saying is look
here's the freedom dividend if you opt
in then you're saying I prefer that to
other stuff so it's not that it's an
either/or but we don't take anything
from anyone so we're not gonna make
anyone worse off but if you opt into
this you're saying I would prefer a
thousand dollars cash unconditional no
reporting no monitoring no requirements
I can spend the money on whatever I want
no you know I would have to compare it
to what I'm already making in Social
Security
yeah yeah that's right and that's one of
the reasons why the cost for this come
down to something much more manageable
because a lot of people just do the
basic math and they're like twelve
thousand dollars for every adult in the
country that's like three trillion
dollars that's a lot but because of the
current spending it actually brings the
price tag down very very quickly and
then if you put on this tech tax where
we have a value-added tax that gets the
gains from all these new innovations and
self-driving cars and trucks like that
gets the price tag down very very fast
so this is much more affordable than
people think now how did you say that
you said that the money is
but then also read about the value at
attack so you want to put 10% on all
goods and services yeah what is it is
the money already there you have to put
the simple syntax on it in order to get
the money well so the reason why there
are all these people who are looking
like a OCR like very high marginal
income tax rate or Elizabeth Warren with
like a wealth tax like we realized that
this economy's gotten entirely
unbalanced where you have you know the
top 1% hoovering up all the gains like
when winner-take-all economy so the
question is how do you balance that out
and and so to me a value-added tax is a
much more efficient way to do it and
it's what every other country is already
done because a value-added tax is very
hard to game like if you're Jeff Bezos
your Amazon you're gonna have to pay it
as long as you're doing business in the
US so you could build the value out of
tax or to exempt certain consumer
staples so it falls more on on the
affluent than people who are just like
buying diapers and the rest of it but
the reason why every other country
that's an advanced economy aside from US
has already done it is that it actually
will get us a slice of every Amazon
transaction every Facebook ad every
Google search every robot truck mile and
bring it to the American people put the
money in our hands and then what are we
gonna do we're gonna spend that money in
the economy it's gonna create two plus
million jobs and Amazon and the gang are
still gonna get some of that money back
you know what I mean but at least it
comes through our hands we are the
owners and shareholders of this country
and this is a dividend for us now let me
ask you question now you talk about
Amazon and I'm down by the way you see
here Oh Marian is not my competition
Marian's awesome you talk about Amazon
with it we're not having tax but let's
say we decide to tax Amazon right
doesn't amazon close up go to a country
someplace where they get huge tax breaks
and then we lose all those jobs again
well again every other advanced economy
already has a value-added tax and
Europe's value-added taxes twice what
I'm proposing so where they gonna go
like we are the number one consumer
market it's how they gonna stop selling
here the other thing is that as
president I would make all of the tax
incentives provided by cities and states
for companies to move a hundred percent
taxable I would get rid of that stuff
because it makes no sense to have cities
and states fighting to give tax breaks
to the Amazons of the world we're from
the National point of view we don't care
what city or state they're in right and
Amazon should be making
choices based upon what's best for their
business not who they can get the
biggest concessions from now you say in
a thousand dollars a month he's saying
free health care
now what about weed and what about
college is free college so yeah and
legalizing marijuana there's a lot of
money to be made from that as well so
don't you think about that and where
should that money go I'm for the
legalization of marijuana remove it from
the controlled substance list in part
because our administration of the
criminal laws are deeply racist it's
very obvious to everyone so on April
20th 2021 I'm gonna pardon everyone
who's in prison for a low-level
nonviolent drug offense I like your
marketing scratches the 4/20 baby
because it makes no sense to have people
in jail for stuff that's legal in some
parts of the country and then there'd be
a lot of money and and I know there are
bills that want to channel that money to
African American businesses and
communities which is a great idea yeah
because we were affected so much by
these marijuana laws yeah completely
there's Andrew yang have a black agenda
do you have an agenda specifically for
black people well a lot of it overlaps
with with my overall agenda cuz I think
that the you know the freedom dividend
and universal health care would go a
long way but I'm for getting rid of
private prisons I think it makes no
sense to have prisons that have a profit
motivation
oh I mean again it affects everyone yeah
I'm for dramatically increasing the
federal allotment HBCUs because the
problem with education right now is it's
become a business and so what happens is
schools and benefitting by catering to
the affluent because I'll donate more
money and they can pay full freight and
the rest of it and so you have these
HBCUs that are of an incredible
historical mission have been shown to
elevate you know hundreds of thousands
of African Americans but because they
don't have these crazy endowments that
some of the rich schools do that they're
struggling and so the federal government
can help shore that up the government in
my mind exists in part to counterbalance
the excesses and perversions of the
marketplace and right now in American
life the market is just running amok
it's over running everything and that's
what we have to stop and the one great
way to stop that get this dividend into
everyone's hands and that'll help us
we claim our democracy why would the top
1% of the country even just people
that's doing well in life need a extra
thousand dollars a month well should it
really be for universal should it really
be for everybody there are so there are
a few reasons why I think it should be
universal well one in this example is
like Jeff Bezos something I'm going to
be paying hundreds of millions billions
of dollars and do it so we don't care if
they get a thousand it's like you know
it's just like a reminder that there's
still a human being in a citizen but if
you try and make it income based it ends
up being a rich to poor transfer and
then it ends up being politicized in a
particular way more if you make it
Universal it's like look it's just
you're in America in your cities and you
get a thousand bucks a month and then
you end up getting rid of all the
administration you get rid of all the
reporting you get rid of all the oh my
circumstances changed or I'm gonna under
report because I want to be below this
line so I can get the money they get rid
of all of that stuff and then you get
rid of the stigma because one of the
problems with our existing programs is
that you know like there's a stigma
attached to being in them and then
everyone politically attacks them and
this you can't attack and Alaska is the
proof because in a deep red state
Alaskans love their dividend so much
that they said they would accept higher
taxes to keep the dividend that's how
much they loved it I see you're also
doing this plan with a couple of
families right you're testing it out to
show how it does work
yeah I'm personally giving a thousand
bucks a month to a family in New
Hampshire and a family in Iowa and
shocker they like it you know that money
oh yeah well if I'm president man I want
to do it for everyone and find the money
okay you would also be making four
million dollars a year as president so
I'm talking about his proposal oh yeah
so my proposals that presidents get a 10
X raise to 4 million dollars but then
they're not allowed to take any for
profit for personal gain speaking fees
or board opportunities or any of that
stuff after the fact because it's human
nature do they finish term is over oh
they can do books but they can't join
corporate boards for money do take
speaking fees for money
because it's human nature let's say I'm
president and then there's some rich
CEOs hanging around in the Oval Office
and I know that three years from now
they can give me four hundred thousand
dollars just to show up and smoothes
with their clients and employees it's
human nature for me to be a little nicer
to them be a little softer on them to be
like oh you know I should just make
friends with this person because I'm
gonna end up hanging out on the jet with
them after I'm president so you get rid
of that motivation you say look I can't
take a dime from anyone for personal
gain you're gonna pay me enough so that
you know I work for the people but
that's it we have to stop worshipping
the almighty dollar and that starts from
the top and this race can go into effect
the president after me I really do not
care we have to clean up our government
so it actually works for us and it's
clear that I'm with that cuz I feel like
presidents of public servants and I feel
like all public servants need to be
getting paid more money teachers police
officers I don't give more your ball
plays than you freaking like
entertainers watch it in the present get
formula yeah yeah and and and then say
no more profit taking after that still a
tough job sir
apparently I know my wife was reading
Michelle Obama's book and apparently the
account for like white house like
household expenses Stockton California
will be the first American city to
experiment with free money yeah I was
with mayor Tubbs on a panel just a few
months ago and you know I I think it's
tremendous that they're funding these
basic income trials in Stockton Mayor
Tom's a great guy I know some of the
people that are funding that trial but I
will say guys like this it's
embarrassing that a lot of the money for
these Charles is coming from private
individuals because coming in the 60s
and 70s the United States government was
giving money to thousands of American
families to test out whether this sort
of program works and it should be the
public sector leading the charge on this
because we're entering the age of AI
we're gonna have self-driving cars and
trucks in five to ten years 30% of malls
are gonna close in the next four years
thanks to Amazon two and a half million
call center workers in the US are going
to get replaced by AI there was a study
in The Guardian that said the the median
african-american household net worth is
going to be
by 2050 3 like in 34 years you guys see
that study no well yeah you should look
it up and so why are they forecasting
that african-american network and worth
is going to go to zero it's because of
this economic tidal wave that is coming
this economic tidal wave is gonna wipe
out many working-class jobs and it's
gonna be it's gonna be the equivalent of
a natural disaster and we know what
happens in a natural disaster who
suffers poor people don't have the
resources people of color and the same
thing is gonna happen in this so that's
why I'm running for president I can see
the tidal wave coming very very clearly
how do you why isn't what's different
between a welfare and government
assistance in you you yeah well the big
shift we have to make is instead of
seeing it as again like Oh like you're
down on your luck like things aren't
working out so here's something to get
you up to a certain point but then if
you do better we take it away like that
that's a way the way a lot of our
current programs are designed in the
dividend you get it you do better you
keep the dividend you keep what you're
making to it aligns your incentives much
more closely and again it gets rid of
the stigma it makes us all shareholders
of our collective progress and then if
someone comes up with some great
innovation you feel like okay at least
I'm getting a little piece of that and
then we can start having a better
attitude towards like our shared future
you know what I love about you Andrew I
love the fact that you're up here
discussing solutions and not problems
you're not running on a anti Trump
campaign you actually have ideas so that
it pains me that you probably don't have
a shot in hell of winning so are you oh
we're gonna find our brother I'm just
are you are you running to actually
Wayne are just to disrupt the system um
we raised almost 600 K last month which
is more than just about every major
candidate except for Bernie and no one's
heard of me so you gotta ask how the
heck did that happen I'm talking sense
and like you say and like you said well
I mean now thanks to you all like some
more people have heard of me which I'm
very happy for but you're right Trump is
a symptom what is the disease the
disease is the fact that we're getting
pushed into economic distress the
disease this is mindset of scarcity that
has overtaken our people because if you
can't pay your bills then it's very very
hard to be clear thinking and optimistic
the future the disease is increasingly
that we're going to be competing against
machines AI software robots that are
going to be able to outdo us in terms of
capital efficiency this is the disease
so how do you cure the actual disease
most politicians do not want to touch
this with a ten-foot pole because they
don't have real solutions and the
solution I'm gonna suggest is that we
share the bounty from all this economic
progress as fast as possible and that's
why I'm running for president build the
wall around Silicon Valley that has to
be your slogan you know you know what
about this what about this Lander you
know Donald Trump goes hard he will
slander everybody are you ready for that
you ready to get down dirty with the
shenanigans well we we joke around the H
cube what his nickname for me is gonna
be and we've come up with comrade yang
comrade yang why comrade yang you know
because it's a little bit like racially
tinged it makes me seem like this far
out socialist you know that sort of
thing and I'm looking forward to this I
mean these guys in Iowa came up to me
and they said I voted for Donald Trump
I'm gonna vote for you one person said
you're actually what I hope for when I
voted for Donald Trump Wow
so I can get some Trump supporters
behind me because I'm trying to address
the same problems that got him elected
but whereas his solutions were all
backwards it was like build the wall
turn the clock backwards bring back the
jobs I'm saying we have to turn the
clock forwards we have to accelerate our
society and our notions of our own value
and work and one of the examples I use
is my wife is at home with our two kids
six and three one of whom is autistic
and right now the market values her work
at zero GDP values her work at zero and
that's completely messed up we know the
work she's doing is more valuable and
difficult and important absolutely and
so we need to evolve in the way we see
value and this thousand dollar-a-month
dividend one of the things that would do
right now there are millions of American
women in exploitative or abusive jobs or
relationships because they lack the
economic freedom to actually make a
change in their situation so the
Democratic Party's going to talk about
empowering women you know it's gonna
empower women a thousand bucks a month
you know you get a thousand bucks a
month and then you know you're in some
job that's exploiting you or some like
you know relationship that's not good to
you then you are you the only candidate
that's believing in this universal
basically
I am the only candidate championing yet
thus far but I have a feeling I'm gonna
have some company after it sweeps the
nation everyone wakes up we're in a
democracy there's nothing stopping a
majority of us from declaring ourselves
a dividend nothing at all giving
ourselves some money it's yeah okay
declaring ourselves yeah so what happens
in like corporate language shareholders
get together and declare themselves a
dividend okay so this is what happens
with like Microsoft or coca-cola they're
like hey we're sitting on all this money
let's declare a dividend for ourselves
so what I'm saying is there's nothing
stopping the majority of citizens of a
country from declaring ourselves a
dividend there's nothing at all and
after people wake up to that reality
then it's gonna sweep the nation and
then I have a feeling a bunch of other
Democrats are gonna be like you know
what I'm kind of for that too but first
we need to make the case that this is
what we need to do as a people together
I'm technology wise how do we keep up
but also make sure that people still
aren't losing their jobs to automation
to robots well and so this is really the
danger is that there's already a
reaction where some people are saying
look we need to outlaw robot trucks
because there's so many people that rely
upon that job there are three and a half
million truckers there another five
million Americans who work at truck
stops and hotels and diners that rely
upon the truckers getting out every day
and having a meal so it would be
disastrous to replace those truckers
with robots
in the next five to ten years but on the
other hand you're looking at accidents
that kill 4,000 people a year with human
truck drivers then you might be able to
reduce that number you're looking at
fuel efficiency savings because the
robot trucks can convoy together and
there's lower wind resistance so it's
actually good for the earth maybe if you
have robot trucks and all the stuff that
they're creating now right now my wife's
car I can't get into an accident I
cannot hit or miss a good karma vehicles
as well so what I'm saying is that where
America does not want to be in is in a
let's stop progress mode and we are
inching towards the let's stop progress
mode because I'm
I'll look up and be like wait is this
really what we want they're gonna be a
lot of truckers that protest robot
trucks 100% and only 13% of truck
drivers are unionized so there's no
collective negotiation at bargain most
of these truckers like small mom-and-pop
owned their own trucks etc etc and so
they're going to be protests and the
question is what are we doing as a
country so my plan is to say look this
is such a massive transition that we
should have a truck or transitions are
who takes some of the gains from where
about trucks and starts trying to create
a soft landing for displaced truckers
and the freedom dividend and trying to
reconstitute our economy as fast as we
can this is what pisses me off about the
a a conversation if robots are gonna
take over the world
let's just stop building them we're the
ones building the robots it's off switch
we keep building he's talking about the
benefits of having that because it will
cut down on other things like you said
accidents and better for the earth
better for the earth it's gonna save 168
billion dollars a year and so if you're
the United States and you're literally
like hey guys let's ban robot trucks and
then every other major economy has to
keep that you really are shooting
yourself in the foot you're like hey
we're literally gonna spend an extra
hundred sixty eight billion dollars to
maintain these trucker jobs and the
trucker jobs are really physically
demanding and brutal like 80% of the
trucker's have early markers for chronic
disease they're sitting in a truck
you know like eleven twelve hours a day
to make money yeah so this is the
question and this is and it's not just
the truckers man I mean like I saw what
happened the manufacturing workers what
happened to them is gonna happen to the
truckers we don't talk about it as much
but being a retail clerks the most
common job in this country even a tolls
and bridges there's no more there's no
real tolls and building the robots don't
hit the off switch or we just start
dispensing the bounty as fast as
possible and we start so if you imagine
a country after I'm president 2021
freedom dividend goes out what do you
see a massive increase in arts
creativity journalism entrepreneurship
volunteering participation in you know
nonprofits and religious organizations
like all that stuff's gonna surge after
you put twelve thousand dollars a year
into everyone's hands and so when you
talk about the meaning of life
Charlemagne I mean like I'm gonna
suggest that that that is the question
of this era like what are the truck
drivers gonna do yeah like that that is
the question and we have to start trying
to provide real answers instead of you
don't need a job you can't just say what
are they gonna do they go be is gonna be
hurt did a lot of people lot of people
are losing jobs now because it is real
bad just told well do you think that we
need to retrain people about technology
and learning how to code and learning
how to do other things to be more
advanced all right so this is something
I get really really animated about we
can talk about turning coal miners into
software engineers or whatever but the
reality is that if you're you know if
you're you've been a coal miner for 20
years or trucker for 12 years like
there's no reason to think that you're
gonna like being a software engineer or
that you can become a Kesava engine you
just might not be smart enough only 8%
of jobs are in STEM fields and 92% are
not so saying hey we're gonna somehow
turn the 92 percent into the 8% like
does not make any sense and the only
reason you're even trying is because
you're so brainwashed by the market
logic where you're like oh if you don't
have economic value then you have no
value and so because your job doesn't
work now I'm gonna have to turn you into
a coda or something which is ridiculous
on its face so we have to start valuing
ourselves intrinsically and design an
economy that actually works for human
beings to your point Charlemagne it's
like the kind of doesn't work for us
what's the point yeah so what we have to
do instead of measuring capital
efficiency and GDP we have to start
measuring things like childhood success
rates mental health and freedom from
substance abuse environmental quality
you know proportion of elderly that can
retire in quality circumstances this is
a way we actually measure the economy
before we invented GDP we ended vented
GDP almost 100 years ago during the
Great Depression and even the inventor
said is a terrible measurement for
national well-being we should not use it
as that and now we're gonna follow it
off a cliff so the big evolution is to
say look we're gonna value ourselves in
more human terms we're gonna build an
economy that works around us and then we
can start answering the the fundamental
challenges that got Donald Trump elected
now what about gun laws as far as gun
laws yeah so I'm a parent I think that
we need to treat gun owner
ship in a very similar way to the way we
treat vehicle ownership like look you
get a you get you have to take a test
and get a license to drive a vehicle and
that could kill people guns can kill
people too so we should give you some
kind of test and licensing for that too
the there's a hard part the challenge of
this is that there are 300 million farms
in this country it's like almost one for
every man woman and child and there are
limited ways you can actually try and
reduce that number so a couple things I
would do is I would have a voluntary gun
buyback anyone who wants to sell their
gun will buy it off you and I would also
offer to upgrade everyone's guns to
those signature guns where only you can
fire them turn everyone's gun into a
James Bond and then we're safer because
that gun goes to someone else and they
can't fire yeah and that that's
something it's actually not that
expensive to upgrade a gun to a
signature gun all the guns you know it's
a value of the gun but like I would say
that that's a win for the public and you
know that you sound like anyone's gonna
go and sell they're going all at once
but these are the sorts of things out
before I'm for trying to provide like
more positive alternatives than move our
society in the right way without
pretending frankly that we can just
regulate the heck out of everything and
so as an example of this our democracy
has gotten too overrun by corporate
money we can all see it and so a lot of
people like overturn Citizens United
which I agree with but what I would do
is I would give every American adult a
hundred democracy dollars that you can
only give it to a political candidate
every year and it's user loser you don't
use it it disappears you've got to turn
America into a monopoly and this would
like wash away the corporate money
because then if I get human beings
behind me I also get the money whereas
right now if I get the human beings
behind me I have to go someplace where
they're rich people and be like hey you
want to give me some money and it's the
worst like calling rich people for money
is soul-crushing so what you want to do
is you want to try and make it so that
if I get again real life Americans
behind me then they're like I like this
guy here's 50 democracy dollars and then
we human beings as if you're not one I
say for the past ten minutes one
interview really a robot pinch me
brother pinch me do that like I make
them real real nowadays
I'm very convinced no answer that and
even with taxes right you talked about
doing your taxes kind of like gaming
yeah so so when you think about so
running the government like a business
is nonsense they're two very different
things but one thing that the government
can learn from business is that
businesses don't treat their customers
like crap and our government treats us
like crap come tax day we're giving the
government hundreds of billions of
dollars and do we ever get like any kind
of like celebration of that fact I mean
if we're customers people would be like
oh my gosh it was like hundreds of
billions of dollars so I would make tax
day into a national holiday I would call
it revenue day I would have it so that
AI tries to pre-fill out your taxes for
you so if you're very simple taxes that
are based upon the same info it just
gets spit out for you and then you'd get
a video showing where your money's going
you know government employees thanking
you and then you can choose where to
send the last 1% of your money being
like you know what I really want to fund
these programs and then there'd be
someone from that program being like
well thank you for choosing this program
then you get Oprah and Tom Hanks and The
Rock in on this video and then we'd
actually not mind revenue day because
we'd be like oh and then I invite
families from every state to the White
House and celebrate our society's real
instead of treating tax day like this
thankless chore that we all dread oh
it's like oh you nut that America tell
me thank you my people fought here and
built this country for 400 freaking you
yeah let me think you want to activate
yes money you take it from me FICO yes
simple thank you you know we just saw
white there earlier every time that you
want to simple thank you yes yes no no
what about you know banking banking is
difficult especially in African
communities it's hard to get low
african-american that's African hard to
get loans what can we do to help people
get loans to spot to start small
businesses so there's the beauty of the
freedom dividend man cuz like money
follows money you know like if you have
african-american communities where
everyone's getting 12,000 bucks a year
then all of a sudden the businesses in
that community start being more
lucrative and profitable and then if I'm
a lender I'm like heck yes you want a
loan like sign me up
and then they'll start investing in
those communities because the market
will drive them in that direction and if
that doesn't work that will do more but
I think the Mar that like the best way
we can empower African American
businesses to put money into the hands
of African American I think to town I
think you should think mm you know the
best way to power African American
businesses put money in hands African
Americans yeah so I think you should do
$2,000 a month oh my gosh envy and we're
gonna we're gonna start with tube we're
gonna start we'll start with one and
then maybe my second term when
everyone's loving that first dividend I
I read Tana he see coats and I 100%
agree with the moral case for
reparations this country was built on
the backs of slaves and you know there
there's no two ways about it
so to me the question is what can we get
done there's nothing that we can do as a
society that would actually undo that
harm or I mean that right there there is
no redoing history but the path forward
to me if we put this dividend in place
and at least it starts strengthening
communities and then we can take real
steps forward towards hopefully again
can't make things right but hopefully
you can start moving things in the right
direction
Andrew yang I like you sir thank you man
I like you all right well I feel like
you'll be back here again I'll be back
any time you guys want because like my
coolness factor does went up
significantly and I've got a copy that
book for you Angela I got copies for
each of you I signed that one for
Charlemagne might be another one in the
room for you and and for DJ envy thank
you so I wouldn't come unprepared like
that I almost read your books man I try
and be prepared but like I appreciate
the fact that you talk openly about you
know struggles and and emotional issues
my brother is a psychology professor oh
wow and so one of the goals I'm gonna
have as presidents I'm gonna have a
psychologist in the White House to help
D stigmatize the struggles that people
go through and also stuff yeah yeah yeah
it's real I mean everyone struggles with
it particularly people that you know
have been through a lot was your brother
built what lab was he building um you
know he's the prototype they improved on
it for me I'm like liquid metal God you
know
my brother's more like Arnie true true
true all right well thank you for
joining us man wish you the best of luck
and give me a card website so they can
donate to your campaign oh yeah hey guys
so this is actually a good thing for the
campaign so my website's yang 2020 com
or you can just google Andrew yang but
in order to make the democratic debates
I need 65,000 individual contributors
and I'm gonna get there like right now
we're at like 46 thousand and I'm gonna
get there in a minute but if you want to
be part of getting me on the debate
stage just go to yang 2020 comm and
donate a buck and let's make this case
together we got to solve the problems
you were platted people to say thank you
I really do I tried it very much yeah
it's like really I'm immensely grateful
to everyone who's gotten this campaign
to this point and you haven't seen
nothing yet
I mean we're gonna go very very far
together I think you're a great
disruption sir all right well Andrew
yang there's so much coming through its
The Breakfast Club good morning